<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kyle Davidson</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 16:57:43 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 16:57:43 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>AWS Cognito</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just over a year ago I evaluated &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/cognito/&quot;&gt;AWS Cognito&lt;/a&gt; and it’s suitability for a digital service project in Kainos. This is a large solution that aims to become a centralised system for collecting and processing a specific sector of information in the UK. It’s a highly active environment with around 3 million events carried out per year. These activities have an estimated economic impact of £4 billion per annum and operate in a highly complex ecosystem between local authorities, utility companies, third party contractors and specialist software vendors. We use AWS Cognito to support these 500+ organisations and their users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated AWS Cognito is a secure and scalable user directory. It has features like &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/cognito-user-pools-identity-federation.html&quot;&gt;federated third-party sign-in&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/cognito-sync.html&quot;&gt;cross-device-syncing&lt;/a&gt; but in the case of our project it was chosen for its standards-driven authentication and authorisation capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14 months later, the project is now in private beta and in that time we’ve learnt quite a few things about Cognito that may be useful to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;early-days&quot;&gt;Early days&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine Cognito’s suitability I authored an &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/kainos/you-must-think-first-before-you-move-7ac4af0346a9&quot;&gt;Open Design Proposal&lt;/a&gt; in May 2018 which was submitted to our development team. It detailed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How we could use Cognito for authentication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How we could use Cognito for authorisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How we might implement Cognito flows (sign-up, sign-in, reset-password)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non functional concerns (security, data-ownership, migration, costs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ODP was followed up with a proof-of-concept I had developed using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/cognito-user-pools-app-integration.html&quot;&gt;Hosted UI&lt;/a&gt; provided by Cognito.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/cognito-sign-up.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sign-up&quot; height=&quot;248&quot; width=&quot;248&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/cognito-sign-in.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sign-up&quot; height=&quot;248&quot; width=&quot;248&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is quite a barebones interface it still validated the most significant benefits to using Cognito for our project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A plug and play authentication layer with customisable password policy controls we wouldn’t have to build ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognito provided &lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7519&quot;&gt;JSON web tokens&lt;/a&gt; which we could use in our authorisation layer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A well documented SDK available in many languages (in our case Node.js)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant limitations we found at the time were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Custom attributes are not searchable as they cannot be indexed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognito does not provide an option to export users increasing vendor lock-in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hosted UI did not offer suitable customisation controls for our &lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/&quot;&gt;GDS compliant web UI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it was very easy to get started with Cognito and coming off of a project where we had built and managed our own user directories with &lt;a href=&quot;https://backstage.forgerock.com/docs/opendj&quot;&gt;OpenDJ&lt;/a&gt; as well as maintained our own authentication and authorisation controls, the immediate benefits were clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team we decided that it was a good fit, our project was already AWS heavy and we were keen to go with a managed service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-good-stuff&quot;&gt;The Good Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authentication and authorisation in our project works like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users login to our system using an authentication endpoint on our API&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The API uses the AWS Cognito SDK to authenticate the user&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If successful, Cognito brings us back ID, Access and Refresh tokens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We give the tokens back to the user, which they in turn use for future requests via an &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/Authorization&quot;&gt;Authorization header&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/cognito-authr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sign-up&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any request to a secure endpoint in our application expects and validates the token provided in this header. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/amazon-cognito-user-pools-using-tokens-verifying-a-jwt.html&quot;&gt;Verifying a JWT&lt;/a&gt; in Cognito is well documented and straight-forward. We even found a node package which bundles the steps up for us called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/cognito-express&quot;&gt;cognito-express&lt;/a&gt; but we found it gave us less control around logging and health monitoring than we wanted so we wrote our own small service to carry out the validation instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognito has given us a well documentated and flexible authentication layer with flows for sign-up, sign-in, sign-out, forgot-password, administrative invites, resets, disabling and more. Furthermore the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/cognito-user-pools-user-groups.html&quot;&gt;group&lt;/a&gt; functions have given us an access control layer that has held up to this day. The JSON web tokens have allowed us to build a secure authorisation layer with virtually no effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the type of solution you’re building you may never come across the same challenges we have, but I think they are good to know in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;amplify-js&quot;&gt;Amplify JS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aws-amplify.github.io/&quot;&gt;Amplify JS&lt;/a&gt; is essentially a wrapper around the AWS SDK giving you an easy to use interface to a bunch of different services, including Cognito. We used this early on in the project and came across massive issues with how this framework uses the browser’s localStorage for a large amount of it’s Cognito utilities. We caught on pretty early but in my opinion the docs are misleading and imply the framework is suitable for a Node.JS project. It polyfills the window object and server-side &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/code&gt; was a literal &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt;. This lead to fun behaviours we found when testing our application like one user signing-out signed every user out. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aws-amplify/amplify-js/issues/876&quot;&gt;Other people have had problems using Amplify with Node&lt;/a&gt;. Eventually we just moved to using the SDK directly and as a result seen significant performance improvements to response times around our Cognito driven endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re building a mobile app or working with a client-side technology then Amplify is a good choice. Ultimately this library just calls onto the actual SDK so if you want to have these functions server-side I would recommend you just use the SDK directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;custom-attributes&quot;&gt;Custom Attributes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognito comes with a ton of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/user-pool-settings-attributes.html&quot;&gt;standard attributes&lt;/a&gt; you can use, as well as reasonable custom attribute options. Where you run into trouble is if you need to list and search for users using one of these custom attributes. Given that they cannot be indexed, they are not searchable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;exporting-users&quot;&gt;Exporting Users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you can import users into Cognito from a CSV file, there is no option at this point to export users out of Cognito. However depending on your needs you could &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito-user-identity-pools/latest/APIReference/API_ListUsers.html&quot;&gt;list the users&lt;/a&gt; out into a CSV file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rate-limits--errors&quot;&gt;Rate limits &amp;amp; Errors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognito defines a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cognito/latest/developerguide/limits.html&quot;&gt;soft &amp;amp; hard limits&lt;/a&gt; but when we exceeded one of the API limits we couldn’t really get any useful information about what rate we hit. Cognito raises a generic ‘Rate exceeded’ error and we were told by AWS support that there are no metrics for Cognito and throttling available to keep a track of API calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project has been using Cognito for over a year now. Where it has really shined for us is it’s authentication and access controls but it has also allowed us to build administrative and standard user journeys at a much lower cost than if we had built our own user services. I still think there could be a few improvements made around querying users, the group features are great for RBAC but something simple to let me group and query users by a department or organisation would go a long way for the type of enterprise projects I’ve worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would absolutely recommend Cognito for a new project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cloud/2019/07/21/AWS-Cognito.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cloud/2019/07/21/AWS-Cognito.html</guid>
        
        <category>cloud</category>
        
        <category>digital services</category>
        
        
        <category>cloud</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Elevator Pitch - Express.js</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I touched on in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/02/Node.html&quot;&gt;Node JS&lt;/a&gt; pitch, with Node we have a platform to build fully Javascript applications, even all the way down to the database layer if we use a JSON based DB like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Express JS&lt;/strong&gt; exists to make development on Node faster and easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;express-js&quot;&gt;Express JS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web application framework for Node JS, which utilises the HTTP module for Node I talked about in the previous blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-it-is&quot;&gt;What it is&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to configure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great for building both front-end applications and API’s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to integrate with template engines (e.g. Pug, Handlebars, Mustache)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to connect with DB layers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;express-101&quot;&gt;Express 101&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Express can be installed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/&quot;&gt;NPM&lt;/a&gt;. with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install express&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous Node JS blog, we were able to spin up a web server to handle our requests to port 8080. The same thing can be achieved, and then some, with Express like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// app.js&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'express'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Hello World'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;listen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8080&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Node server is running..'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see this is quite similar to the set-up we did in the Node blog, the difference being at the top we’ve included the Express module and initialised it to a variable called app, this has given us an Express application context which we can then define routes on easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of the Express ecosystem is &lt;strong&gt;Middleware&lt;/strong&gt;, you can think of them as chainable functions that run between the client request and the server response. They can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Execute code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make changes to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;res&lt;/code&gt; objects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End the request-response cycle or trigger the next middleware function in the stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of the built in middleware with Express is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://expressjs.com/en/4x/api.html#express.static&quot;&gt;express.static&lt;/a&gt; serves static assets such as HTML files, images, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://expressjs.com/en/4x/api.html#express.json&quot;&gt;express.json&lt;/a&gt; parses incoming requests with JSON payloads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://expressjs.com/en/4x/api.html#express.urlencoded&quot;&gt;express.urlencoded&lt;/a&gt; parses incoming requests with URL-encoded payloads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another middleware module which is particularly useful is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/expressjs/body-parser&quot;&gt;body-parser&lt;/a&gt; which allows us to easily parse incoming request bodies. Like any module, it can be installed using NPM &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install body-parser&lt;/code&gt;and here’s how we could use it in combination with Express to create a basic REST API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// app.js&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'express'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;bodyParser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;body-parser&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;use&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;bodyParser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;urlencoded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;extended&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}));&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/apples'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fake_db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/apples/:id'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fake_db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;404&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Apple not found&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/apples'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'color:'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'brand'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;brand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fake_db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;201&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;put&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/apples/:id'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'color:'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'brand'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;brand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fake_db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;update&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/apples/:id'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fake_db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;apples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;listen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8080&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Node server is running..'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can see with Express we can quickly define routes and the methods that can be performed on them, furthermore the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bodyParser&lt;/code&gt; middleware module gave us easy access to request bodies through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req.body&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;template-engines&quot;&gt;Template Engines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to web front-ends in Express, using a template engine enables you to use static template files which at runtime are transformed into HTML files, this includes populating any variables defined in a template file with actual values. This approach makes it easier to design an HTML page and is especially useful in combination with REST API’s where you could define one template to represent many resources of the same type.  As a quick example, we will use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/pug&quot;&gt;pug&lt;/a&gt; template engine, again this can be installed via NPM &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install pug&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can define a template and use it in our Express application like so, in this example I’ve created a folder in my project called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;views&lt;/code&gt; which contains the template file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// index.pug
html
  head
    title=title
  body
    h1= message

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then in my Express application I can do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// app.js&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'express'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;express&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'views'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'./views'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'view engine'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'pug'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'/'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;render&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'index'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Hello World'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Welcome to my website!'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you make a request to the ‘/’ page, the index.pug file will be rendered as HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/03/Express.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/03/Express.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>digital services</category>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Elevator Pitch - Node.js</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;node-js&quot;&gt;Node JS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node.js is a server side runtime environment powered by Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-it-is&quot;&gt;What it is&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lightweight with some handy built-in modules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asynchronous by default&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scalable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A platform that can allow us to write a full end-to-end Javascript application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-it-isnt&quot;&gt;What it isn’t&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-Threaded&lt;/strong&gt;: Node runs in a single process and the application code runs in a single thread, so while it is asynchronous, certain long-running calculations or complex tasks can block other incoming requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;node-101&quot;&gt;Node 101&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how we can create a Node JS web server and that will handle HTTP requests to port 8080.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-Javascript&quot;&gt;// my_server.js
const http = require('http');

const server = http.createServer((req, res) =&amp;gt; {
  res.statusCode = 200;
  res.setHeader('Content-Type', 'text/plain');
  res.end('Hello World\n');
});

server.listen(8080)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we accessed port 8080 on the browser we would see “Hello World”. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;require('http');&lt;/code&gt; line above imports one of Node’s core modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modules&lt;/strong&gt; are just functionality organised into Javascript files that can be reused under a common namespace. We could just as easily create our own module by creating a Javascript file and adding some code to the special &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; object provided by Node:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-Javascript&quot;&gt;// my_module.js
exports.myDateTime = function () {
    return Date();
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-Javascript&quot;&gt;// my_server.js
const http = require('http');
const myModule = require('./my_module.js')

const server = http.createServer((req, res) =&amp;gt; {
  res.statusCode = 200;
  res.setHeader('Content-Type', 'text/plain');
  res.end('Hello World, here is the time: ' + myModule.myDateTime());
});

server.listen(8080)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some handy core module’s provided by Node include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Module&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/api/http.html&quot;&gt;http&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;classes, methods and events to create http servers&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/api/url.html&quot;&gt;url&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;methods for url parsing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/api/querystring.html&quot;&gt;querystring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;methods to deal with query strings&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/api/util.html&quot;&gt;util&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;utility functions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;node-package-manager&quot;&gt;Node Package Manager&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com&quot;&gt;NPM&lt;/a&gt; is a command line tool that provides dependancy management for your Node.js application. It allows you to install, update or uninstall packages in your application with ease. And provides an online repository for open-source Node.js packages from the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;frameworks-for-node-js&quot;&gt;Frameworks for Node JS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even from my basic code example’s above you can see that when just using Node, the code required to write an actual Web Application is fairly low-level. Yet Node provides us with a solid foundation for developing front-end appications and API’s. So it should be no suprise there are various third party open-source frameworks available in Node Package Manager which makes Node.js application development fast and easy. For example: &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/03/Express.html&quot;&gt;Express JS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/02/Node.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming/2018/05/02/Node.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>digital services</category>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Elevator Pitch - Knockout JS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven’t blogged anything in ages but I want somewhere I can fire up some quick high level summaries of technologies I’m working with. It’s for my own reference really but hopefully if you’re reading this you can find some use in it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;knockout-js&quot;&gt;Knockout JS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the 10 billion Javascript libraries out there, this one is for building &lt;strong&gt;dynamic UI’s with Javascript&lt;/strong&gt; using the Model-View-View Model (MVVM) pattern. So basically if you find yourself writing a load of Javascript that’s injecting big HTML blobs all over the place, Knockout is your friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-it-is&quot;&gt;What it is&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lightweight &amp;amp; small&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supported by a ton of browsers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Akin to some other frameworks which have data-binding features (Angular, Ember or whatever)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-it-isnt&quot;&gt;What it isn’t&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An application framework - it’s not like Angular where it drives your entire application, it’s just a handy library for easy two-way data binding with some extra plugins you could optionally use such as form validation. It doesn’t control how you build the application. In my case I used Knockout with &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;knockout-101&quot;&gt;Knockout 101&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the key points of MVVM. You define your view-model in Javascript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;AppViewModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;firstName&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Kyle&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;lastName&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Davidson&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Activates knockout.js&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;applyBindings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;AppViewModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then bind this to your html (the view) using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data-bind&lt;/code&gt; attribute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;First name: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;strong&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text: firstName&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Last name: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;strong&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text: lastName&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text binding assigns text to those DOM elements, using the values from our view-model. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ko.observable&lt;/code&gt; type will allow our properties to automatically issue notifications whenever their values change. That way any changes to the properties will be reflected on the UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other popular &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data-bind&lt;/code&gt; options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;value&lt;/code&gt;: links the associated DOM element’s value with a property on your view model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;First name: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;input&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;value: firstName&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;visible&lt;/code&gt;: causes the associated DOM element to become hidden or visible according to the value you pass to the binding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;visible: shouldShowMessage&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;	
    You will see this message only when &quot;shouldShowMessage&quot; holds a true value.
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a more popular scenario, let’s say you wanted to build an HTML list out of an array of objects in Javascript. Using fruit as an example, we can declare a model for our fruit objects and build an observable array in the view model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Class to represent a fruit&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Fruit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;colour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;price&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;colour&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;colour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;price&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;price&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Class to represent the view model&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;AppViewModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fruits&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;observableArray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Fruit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Apple&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Green&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;3.50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Fruit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Orange&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Orange&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;3.40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Fruit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Banana&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Yellow&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;3.30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Activates knockout.js&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ko&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;applyBindings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;AppViewModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for-each&lt;/code&gt; data-bind option, we can easily generate a list from these objects like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;ul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;foreach: fruits&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Name: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text: name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Colour: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text: colour&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Price: &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data-bind=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text: price&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we’re using an observable array, any changes to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fruits&lt;/code&gt; array will be reflected in the html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-features&quot;&gt;Other features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computed properties&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event handlers (click, hover etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Templating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Custom bindings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much everything I’ve said is covered in their great &lt;a href=&quot;http://knockoutjs.com/documentation/introduction.html&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming/2017/10/25/Knockout.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming/2017/10/25/Knockout.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>digital services</category>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Wealth of mHealth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend I attended the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mhealth.be/en/home/&quot;&gt;mHealth&lt;/a&gt; hackathon in Belgium with a team of developers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/marekkaluzny&quot;&gt;Marek&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/matthewfitch23&quot;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PMc_A&quot;&gt;Peter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/iSteveyBrown&quot;&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt;. As a group we have a lot of experience with hackathons, myself having competed in Dublin, Liverpool and Barcelona. Generally the format across these types of events is the same, a mix of healthcare and technology professionals get together to pitch ideas, form teams and build a prototype solution. However, this one was a bit different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kick off the event, the team captains pitched their ideas and afterwards these were hung up around the room. Each participant was given 3 post-it notes to stick on those they would like to help build. The problem we wanted to help solve was medication adherence. This is a huge problem in healthcare with billions lost each year because patients forget to take their medication or simply don’t want to continue taking it for other reasons e.g. side effects. Our idea was to build a mobile solution that would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Allow a patient to manage their active prescriptions and view details on dosage, possible side effects etc.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Receive configurable reminders and notifications to take their medication&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide an open communication stream with the patient's circle of care&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/InitialPitch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our Idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially when we pitched this idea many people thought we simply intended to build a reminder application. Which is understandable given the hundreds of existing apps that act as glorified alarm clocks. The real focus of our solution was establishing the connection between the patient and their circle of care. Again, this is not some new idea that hasn’t been seen before, healthcare solutions of course exist in which a mobile application communicates with some cloud platform to connect A to B. The problem is these existing solutions are bespoke; isolated to the context of their service. What we proposed was an application backed by a platform built upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html&quot;&gt;FHIR&lt;/a&gt;, an open standard for communicating healthcare information. We wanted a solution that could be implemented into existing systems, not replace them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were a team of 5 developers, we needed domain knowledge, someone to validate our idea. Thankfully, the very unique thing about this event was the sheer amount of healthcare professionals we had: high profile doctors, pharmacists, nurses and entrepreneurs we had access to. We met &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KatrienApers&quot;&gt;Katrien&lt;/a&gt;, a nurse who works with existing solutions similar to what we wanted to build. We explained our idea to her and she joined our team to help us throughout the weekend. Each team was given a room to work in, again something not traditionally seen at hackathons as usually they’re open plan so people can bounce around and talk to each other more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially we were concerned about this but actually it worked very well, because such a large amount of healthcare professionals were available at this event many just moved around rooms, popping in and having discussions with each team. The thing we noticed right away though was this discussion wasn’t technical focused, numerous times we explained our idea to a clinician, a business analyst for pharmaceutical companies and researchers but much of the feedback was business focused. What was our market and competitors? Who would our first customers be? We realised we didn’t have answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/discussion_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Discussion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-business&quot;&gt;The Business&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That night there was a workshop around creating a Business Model Canvas, initially this is something we didn’t pay much attention to. As developers we were more focused on creating a Kanban board, we broke down our idea into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/agile/user-stories&quot;&gt;user stories&lt;/a&gt; and explained the development process to Katrien who was very interested to see how things were built from our side of the fence. She quickly understood the concept and began creating user stories from the clinician’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up talking to a pharmacist trained business analyst from another team who had been walking around chatting to the other participants. He told us many of the other teams only had 1 or even no developers. A team with no developers shocked us, what were they building this weekend? It seemed some teams were approaching this event like a start-up weekend. We met one team without developers with an idea similar to ours and offered to join the groups so that we could develop while they focused on the business value however their captain didn’t want to do this because he wanted to carry on the idea as a business afterwards and didn’t want 5 developers from one company involved. We understood his concerns but we explained this is something we volunteered to do for the experience and opportunity to build something cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmacist we met asked us about our Business Model Canvas, of course at this moment we still didn’t have one. Honestly we didn’t see the importance of it, we were focused on building the product and we thought it was something focused around making money, which to us wasn’t important. We asked him if he could explain to us how it works and he drove an hour-long discussion about our product as a business. He helped us to establish the detail of our marketing channels, value propositions, revenue streams and cost structures. As developers our customer ended at the patient. This solution was for them to make their life easier, but what we hadn’t thought about was the business value this solution could bring for the likes of pharmaceutical companies and governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/discussion_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Discussion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of our new business analyst friend and some very helpful healthcare business experts, we identified that governments involved in reimbursing expensive medications that had been wasted could be interested in using our application as a mandatory companion with important and expensive medications. They could require patients to use the application in order to ensure the medication was being adhered to and if not, understand why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally the data we would collect around medication and feedback would be very valuable to pharmaceutical companies. What are the most adhered to medications? What are the most common reasons Medication A isn’t adhered to? What are the reasons Medication B is? There was a clear opportunity here for Big Data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-pitch&quot;&gt;The Pitch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the last day of the event our roles had completely changed from developers to full-circle. Each of us were having discussions with a wide range of professionals and generating ideas around marketing, sales, UI/UX and investment. Each team was required to pitch a 7-minute presentation and we knew we needed to do something unique to stand out. We expected many presentations to include detailed statistics, diagrams and all sorts of wizardry so we decided to do something very simple and hand-draw our slides. We used simple stick figures to tell a story about Jack and Jill. Jack was a guy who didn’t adhere to his medication for a variety of reasons: sometimes he forget, sometimes he was having negative side effects, but the story of Jack is a short one because nobody really knew what Jack was up to. Jill on the other hand downloaded MediMate, our mobile app that would help Jill remember to take her medication, provide a direct communication stream to her Pharmacist and allow her to be connected to her circle-of-care. Now we would know if Jill was having side effects or struggling to adhere to her medication and would be able to react appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/dry_run.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry Run&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our presentation was a success, we received lots of great feedback around our simple but engaging style, people commended our technical knowledge behind the solution and we were told our knowledge behind what was required to make this solution a reality was very impressive. For us this was a huge compliment. For a hugely development-focused team this whole event was extremely challenging, by the end our mind-sets had completely opened up to think about everything required with our idea, to understand not only what we would build but also how we would operate as a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this was the most challenging and rewarding hackathon I’ve ever attended. It was amazing being able to have these entrepreneurial focused conversations with very important people I would normally never have access to. We validated our idea and fleshed it out in such detail that we would have never accomplished without them. All in all, an amazing opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KatrienApers&quot;&gt;Katrien&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PieterClompen&quot;&gt;Pieter&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://advance.healthcare/&quot;&gt;Advance.Healthcare&lt;/a&gt; team, the superheroes who helped us throughout the weekend and most importantly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kainos.com/&quot;&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; for giving us the opportunity to attend this event. The ‘Crazy Irish Guys’ had a great time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mhealthbe?src=hash&quot;&gt;Twitter Roll&lt;/a&gt; for the event and the team photo, carrying on my tradition of blinking at the wrong time in group photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/medimate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry Run&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/technology/2016/03/20/mHealth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/technology/2016/03/20/mHealth.html</guid>
        
        <category>health</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>business</category>
        
        <category>hackathons</category>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maintaining Large Applications with Storyboards</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-uis-in-ios-development&quot;&gt;Building UIs in iOS Development&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to designing the views in your application, there are 3 approaches at your disposal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Code&lt;/b&gt;: As you would expect, creating and handling all your visual components as well as their positioning, animations and so on, via code. Unless there is a very specific requirement that would force you to do this you really shouldn't. In general, hand coded UIs are tedious, increase the amount of tests required, difficult to refactor and aren't really tangible compared to the visual tools at your disposal.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;NIBs/XIBs&lt;/b&gt;: With nib files, you create and manipulate your user interfaces graphically, using Xcode, instead of programmatically. Because you can see the results of your changes instantly, you can experiment with different layouts and configurations very quickly. You can also change many aspects of your user interface later without rewriting any code. This has been a favourite approach for many and generally successful in larger projects.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Storyboards&lt;/b&gt;: While NIBs give the ability to visually represent individual views, storyboards are a visual tool for laying out not only multiple views but also representing the navigation between them. Since their introduction in iOS 5, storyboards have become ever more popular and the recommended way to design the user interface of your application because they enable you to visualize the appearance and flow of your whole application on one canvas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My stance on the ‘correct’ way to do things is that you should go with the trend of the company whose technology you are using. Since Xcode 5, the default project type uses storyboards, every single demo in last year’s WWDC used storyboards, there’s even more functionality available for visual objects in storyboards than there is in NIB files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-story-with-storyboards&quot;&gt;The Story with Storyboards&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that a storyboard is a single file internally represented by XML, therefore if you have multiple people working in parallel on the same storyboard file merge conflicts will be inevitable and not easily resolved. As a simple example imagine developer-a and developer-b branch off from master and both make changes to the same storyboard file; even something as simple as changing the position of a label would result in a merge conflict when they sync up:
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/e0acbcdef154d9ecf68f.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could imagine that in a large project with multiple developers these conflicts would get out of hand and be practically impossible to successfully resolve without choosing one set of changes over the other. So how do we deal with this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;break-up-your-storyboards&quot;&gt;Break Up Your Storyboards&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to large apps with a bunch of features it would be much better to split out the UI into several storyboards depending on the natural sections/modules of your application. With multiple storyboards the application will be easier to manage and reduces the chance of merge conflicts as you can coordinate work on particular parts of the UI more easily. However this raises the question of how to connect each storyboard together. Before iOS 9 this would typically be done via code like so:
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/e6abdf42476725e9a4b1.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously the problem with this is that we’re making the connection via code and therefore it’s not clear how each of the storyboards in your application are connected without knowing the code base. Well with iOS 9 came a better way - &lt;b&gt;Storyboard References&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ios-9-storyboard-references&quot;&gt;iOS 9 Storyboard References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example let’s create a new tabbed application using the default Xcode template and take a look at the main storyboard file that is created for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Tab Bar Storyboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial Storyboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a tab bar application it’s likely each tab will encompass a hierarchy of views and UI components. In this case it’s easy to identify the natural modules/sections of the UI since it’s really just each tab, so we can begin to split the application up into multiple storyboards. This is known as &lt;b&gt;refactoring&lt;/b&gt;. You can select views in an existing storyboard to be refactored out into a new storyboard by highlighting them and selecting Xcode’s &lt;b&gt;Editor&lt;/b&gt; menu &amp;gt; &lt;b&gt;Refactor to Storyboard&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Refactor to Storyboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Refactor Storyboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will prompt you to give a name for the new Storyboard file that will be created, in my case &lt;b&gt;FirstTab.storyboard&lt;/b&gt; and then it will move the selected views to the new storyboard and insert a storyboard reference in the original storyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Storyboard Reference.png&quot; alt=&quot;Storyboard Reference&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you double click the storyboard reference it will take you to the storyboard file associated with that reference. As well as refactoring existing views into new storyboards you can also create storyboards from scratch and reference them later, for example if we created a new Storyboard file for a new tab in our application called &lt;b&gt;ThirdTab.storyboard&lt;/b&gt; and gave it a view controller it might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Third Tab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Third Tab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Note the View Controller’s properties panel on the right hand side where I’ve checked &lt;b&gt;Is Initial View Controller&lt;/b&gt; - this creates a &lt;b&gt;Storyboard Entry Point&lt;/b&gt; so that any storyboard reference will by default instantiate this view controller when triggered. You can also link to other scenes in the storyboard rather than the initial view controller by setting the &lt;b&gt;Storyboard ID&lt;/b&gt; in the Identity Inspector for the view controller you wish to instantiate.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the storyboard for our third tab created we can then drag in a new Storyboard Reference in &lt;b&gt;Main.storyboard&lt;/b&gt; from the Object Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Object Library.png&quot; alt=&quot;Object Library&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can set the storyboard associated by the storyboard reference by selecting it and choosing the new storyboard from the dropdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Set Storyboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Set Storyboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then all that’s left to do is to Ctrl + Drag from the Tab Bar Controller to our Storyboard Reference to connect them with a Relationship Segue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Set Relationship.png&quot; alt=&quot;Set Relationship&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a new tab on the tab bar for us and Voilà!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Final Storyboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final Storyboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the introduction of storyboard references make it much easier to seperate your application’s UI into manageable, reusable pieces whilst still making it clear how everything hooks together.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/technology/2015/09/07/Building-And-Organizing-Large-Projects-With-Storyboards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/technology/2015/09/07/Building-And-Organizing-Large-Projects-With-Storyboards.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building Dynamic Forms with Angular</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-bit-about-custom-directives&quot;&gt;A bit about Custom Directives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not very familiar with Angular, directives are essentially tags you can apply to a DOM element that tell Angular JS’s html compiler to attach a specified behaviour to it. For example we could use one of the following:
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/2acb0a4c20cbc0d2ffdc.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
In this case we would have created a directive called myForm which could have an associated controller, html template and its own scope. There is a restrict property on directives that defines how you can trigger it, so by default we can use an attribute or an element but you can also match against class name. Typically you’d want to use an element when you are creating a component that is in control of the template and an attribute when you are decorating an existing element with new functionality, but of course it all depends on your project needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-scenario&quot;&gt;The Scenario&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok so you want to build a form in Angular.js, this is easy to accomplish but gets more complicated when the fields are dynamic. We want to be able to provide data about our fields e.g. key, type, label etc to Angular, and build a form using this information. The way we get the data isn’t important, for the sake of this example we’ll assume we get the following JSON back from a service.
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/16a3f98c502787132786.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once our data comes back from some service we can use directives to build our form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designing-directives&quot;&gt;Designing Directives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When naming your directives: use a unique prefix. Try not to name your directives ng-something, as to others this would suggest it is an internal Angular directive, just use something appropriate to what you’re working on and keep it to the convential two-letters, for our project at Kainos Smart I went with sm-*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side note when you name a directive in Javascript you use camelCase, but in html you use it with a hyphen like camel-case&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, in regards to the template associated with your directive, you can either use &lt;b&gt;template&lt;/b&gt; (define the HTML in Javascript) or you can use &lt;b&gt;templateUrl&lt;/b&gt; (a URL to an HTML partial). I personally prefer the latter, there’s more work involved in testing it that way because you need to preload the templates into the &lt;b&gt;$templateCache&lt;/b&gt; for tests but it’s definitely my go-to. Also depending on your needs you can avoid the round trip to the server with templateUrl by using script tags with an id, there’s some trades off there but it’s an option none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets take a look at the first outer most directive, smField.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-field-directive&quot;&gt;The Field Directive&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we want to do here is loop through the field objects in our array response, and build a field directive each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/2c88c58d7098ca69c288.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each iteration, we pass the field object into our directive, along with an object to keep track of all the form data that gets entered. So what you’re left with when the user completes the form is an object that contains keys for each field, along with values from what the user has entered. This is particularly useful because we’re using an isolated scope for our field directive, that is, the directive definition looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/b807657ded3e49294665.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth discussing scope because it can cause a lot of confusion for those new to Angular, especially when working with directives like ng-repeat. You can find a great explanation on scopes &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/angular/angular.js/wiki/Understanding-Scopes&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can define your directive’s scope as one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;False (default)&lt;/b&gt;: The directive does not create a new scope. Do not use this when designing reusable directives,
		you want a reusable component to be independant of the outside world, you should be able to plug it in anywhere in your app
		without relying on or effecting existing scope properties.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;True&lt;/b&gt;: The directive creates a new child scope that prototypically inherits from the parent scope. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;{}&lt;/b&gt;: Directive gets a new isolated scope completey detached from the parent scope. This is the favourable choice here as it means our form can be built up in any part of the application without interfering with the parent scope.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directive communicates to the parent scope to get the properties it needs by defining them on the object using special symbols known as &lt;em&gt;prefixes&lt;/em&gt;. There are 3 types of prefixes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;@&lt;/b&gt;: Text Binding. Whatever is passed in is parsed and returned as a string.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/b&gt;: One Way Binding. Allows a directive to trigger evaluation of an expression in the context of the original scope, at a specific time. Any legal expression is allowed, including an expression which contains a function call. Because of this, &amp;amp; bindings are ideal for binding callback functions to directive behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;=&lt;/b&gt;: Two way Data Binding. Any changes to the bound value are reflected in all scopes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sm-field’s template looks like this:
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/8041371a6fbbdc950873.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use ng-switch to conditionally build a child directive depending on the type of field. At Kainos Smart we have custom directives for many types of form-inputs in which we extend the functionality and provide some custom features, as well as defining some of our own form field types, like a typeahead that queries the Workday API. As you can see these child directives don’t have any attributes to pass in data, that’s because they’re scopes are defined as true, thus inheriting the field and formData objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I will show what the sm-text directive might look like as a very simple text-input with no additional functionality.
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/5a0aa51ed8446b9ac7ee.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
We use formData[field.key] as the model for the input, so if our field key was ‘firstName’ our formData object would have a key-value pair such as &lt;b&gt;firstName: “whatever the user enters”.&lt;/b&gt; that is accessible from formData.firstName, This works well for us as Smart has a repeatable field type which recursively calls the initial &lt;b&gt;sm-field&lt;/b&gt; directive to allow repeatable form sections. So with a completed form we have a nice neat object that can be validated. It might look something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/KyleDavidsonPro/4affc81df1e4582b9025.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/12/07/Building-Dynamic-Forms-with-Angular-Directives.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/12/07/Building-Dynamic-Forms-with-Angular-Directives.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data-Binding Frameworks</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-what-frameworks&quot;&gt;Data what frameworks?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What indeed! I’ve recently been looking into some Javascript frameworks that fall under this category of ‘data binding’. Having focused primarily on iOS development for
the past 2ish years I’d consider myself out of the loop when it comes to web dev. So hopefully if you’re like me and haven’t had much exposure to web technologies you
may find some use in this post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a project that uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;Angular.js&lt;/a&gt; in parts of the front end and was asked to look into &lt;a href=&quot;http://emberjs.com/&quot;&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; as an alternative.
If you’re wondering what these things are they’re basically Javascript frameworks used primarily for single page applications. What I mean by single page applications is, instead of
navigating through a site by accessing different html pages through the url, e.g. mysite.com/about would render about.html, a single page application instead uses a single html file and only
the hash fragment of the URL changes e.g. mysite.com#/about. In this case, we’ll still change the behaviour of the page in regards to what we see, but the page itself stays the same and doesn’t reload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So these frameworks follow the MVC pattern and generally there are 3 key parts/concepts you should understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routing: This involves updating the page in response to the URL hash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Templating: Expressing views with a templating language, for example Handlebars.js&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Binding: Maintaining a synchronization between the model and the view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do some really cool things with these frameworks in a crazy low amount of code. Ember for example has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://emberjs.com/guides/models/the-rest-adapter/&quot;&gt;REST Adapter&lt;/a&gt; that provides
a way to work with your model through your REST api without having to write any boilerplate. The most popular frameworks are arguably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Angular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ember&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knockout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of which are great to work with and achieve generally the same thing, there’s a popular Ember vs Angular debate but to be honest it really falls down to your
preferences in most cases. My personal preference is probably Ember because of their convention principles but that’s not to say I don’t like Angular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-now&quot;&gt;What now?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go try them out when you get some time! I don’t want to get into coding examples and that kind of stuff in this blog, I’ll be doing a Codeslice on Ember.JS on 28th August
which will hopefully be recorded and I can edit this post to include at a later date!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/08/21/Data-Binding-Frameworks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/08/21/Data-Binding-Frameworks.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Google Glass</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;welcome-to-the-world-of-tomorrow&quot;&gt;Welcome to the World of Tomorrow!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend the R&amp;amp;D team at Kainos let me take home a pair of Google Glass for the week to try out the dev kit and play about, there’s been talk of a Google Glass
hackathon and for this weekend it’s good to see how quick development is to pick up for someone without an Android background.
However, first and foremost it’s a sweet ass pair of James Bond glasses so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-product&quot;&gt;The Product&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all honesty I never really looked into much stuff around Glass, I had a vague idea of what it was and I was quite surprised about how they actually look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning: Incoming Selfies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Glass1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glass&quot; height=&quot;124&quot; width=&quot;124&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Glass2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Me with Google Glass&quot; height=&quot;124&quot; width=&quot;124&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Glass3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Me with normal Glasses&quot; height=&quot;124&quot; width=&quot;124&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if it isn’t obvious, from left to right, the Google Glasses, me wearing the Google Glasses, and me wearing my normal glasses. So to be fair,
they look &lt;em&gt;alright&lt;/em&gt;, but I think right now if you were to walk around in Belfast with them people would inform you that you look like a pleb. I love the idea
of having your prescription lenses on the Google Glass though and if you’re into wearable technology, why not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was most surprising to me was the actual size of the screen when you’re wearing the glasses, it’s actually pretty small. I find the text hard to read and
it took me a while to get used to the gestures. Though I have to say the voice recognition on it is solid, I didn’t feel like I had to speak differently for it
to register the correct words, I can just talk with my mumbled accent and it knows what’s up. Probably my favourite thing about it though is the ability
to take pictures and record video, because for all the size of it, the camera is pretty damn good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;google-glass-development&quot;&gt;Google Glass Development&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re looking to build native apps, or ‘Glassware’ for this thing, you use the GDK. There’s also the Mirror API for server programming/web applications but
we won’t get into that here. The GDK is basically a small layer/extension to the Android SDK and so if you’re familiar with Android I’d imagine you’ll have a
smooth experience getting started on Glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a decent resource to get started, best bet is &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/glass/&quot;&gt;Glass Developer Docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say I feel like it takes a few hours to get comfortable with the technology and getting set up with a dev environment etc.
But, these things are expected. None the less, I think there will be a lot of interest
for a hack day with Glass. There’s plenty of applicability for Glassware, especially for health related applications. In fact,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/al1ra/status/485753878030585856&quot;&gt;Ali Rawashdeh&lt;/a&gt; has been building Glassware for those affected by colour blindness! Just one
of many possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/07/27/Google-Glass.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/technology/2014/07/27/Google-Glass.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mobilecko</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-donates-blood-reguarly-in-the-uk&quot;&gt;Who donates blood reguarly in the UK?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nobody.&lt;/b&gt; Well, not really but the actual figures aren’t much better, stand back while I copy and paste some research from my dissertation. &lt;i&gt;‘only 4% of people regularly give blood…’ (NHS.uk, 2013). Similarly, in the United States, ‘Although an estimated 38 percent of the U.S. population is eligible to donate blood at any given time, less than 10 percent do so annually.’ (Aabb.org, 2013).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/shock.gif&quot; alt=&quot;shock&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to decide right now you’re going to donate blood for the first time, you’re probably gonna google your way to the Northern Ireland Blood and Transfusion Service’s website, where they provide a list of upcoming mobile donation sessions that can be attended around the country. You give a quick glance for one in your area, lets assume it’s not there, so what do you do? Statistically speaking, you do bugger all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, it’s likely there’s mobile donation sessions in your area frequently, you just don’t give a proactive effort to keep track of that. For all you know you’ve driven past 3 of them on the way to work this week. You’re lazy! But… so are the other 96% of the population, including me. You’d think with the latest Apple 7 and Android Lumia we’d have some kind of app for donating blood wirelessly by now. Well I’ve got some great news…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theres-an-app-for-that&quot;&gt;There’s an app for that!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously not to donate blood wirelessly… are you crazy? That’s imposs- look nevermind. What I’m saying is I built something that allows an organisation such as the NIBTS to be able to have their users download a mobile app that will notify them whenever they are physically near a mobile blood donation session. Obviously, other business markets with an aspect of mobile operation can use this, i.e. food trucks, but let’s stick to blood donation as the use case since it is after all the whole inspiration of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So hopefully the situation that now arises when someone decides they want to donate blood is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They download the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are notified whenever they are physically near a mobile donation session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They donate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the main intention of an increase in lives saved, the idea is to provide features within the application to encourage regular donation, the ability to track progression and share via social networking to create further awareness of blood donation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/yay.gif&quot; alt=&quot;yay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m gonna give a brief run down of how it actually works below but I’ve put a header before that happens so people who don’t care about that side of things can bail out of this blog. Lastly for those interested, &lt;a href=&quot;http://imgur.com/a/DVXFS#4&quot;&gt;Early screenshots of the mobile app&lt;/a&gt;. Keep in mind these screenshots are very early days and do not include the profile system that was created. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kyledavidsonpro.github.io/MobileckoWeb/login.html&quot;&gt;The web client&lt;/a&gt;. Feel free to create an account and play about on it, keep in mind everything is still in development and bugs are likely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;technical-details-below-get-out-while-you-can&quot;&gt;Technical details below, get out while you can&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web client is just a basic html/js site that uses a Parse cloud database to store information on users and their events. Events are restricted through user permissions, i.e. GiveBloodNI wouldn’t be able to see McDonald’s event information etc. Google Geocoder API is used to geolocate the provided event address in order to find out where it is. Any created events can be seen on the Google Map and can be edited on the fly using the table of events (JQuery). Any changes are made asynchronously to Parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mobile client is an iOS application that uses the cloud database to retrieve the event information, store it locally and notify users of upcoming events using the iOS background location and push notification services. There’s a profile system to allow users to log in and share events via Facebook.There’s lots of things I want to do with this down the line but it’s been temporarily shelved until I get sorted within the new job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lukemcneice&quot;&gt;Luke&lt;/a&gt; for all the help with the idea as well as guidance along the way!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming/2014/07/07/Mobilecko.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming/2014/07/07/Mobilecko.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>health</category>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
